Hello, and welcome back to part three
of this AlphaZero tutorial series,
where we're going to take an
in-depth look
at the neural network architecture
that DeepMind used to create
the most powerful intelligence in the world
for playing Go, Chess, and Shogi.
Before we dive in though,
I want to cover a couple of
important concepts
you may not be familiar with.
But, there are tools that can
possibly improve the results
of all your deep learning projects.
The first is batch normalization.
Normalization refers to the process of
squishing widely different values
into the same range usually
between 0 and 1.
Normalizing input data speeds up training,
smooth gradients, and makes
a training more stable.
Meaning you are less likely to
get stuck in a local optimum,
and the loss is more likely to
continuously drop
rather than spike all over the place.
If the input layer is
benefiting from it,
why not do the same thing for
all the hidden layers.
It turns out
the benefits are synergistic.
Batch normalization allows each layer
of a network to learn by itself
a little more independently
of the other layers.
It also helps reduce overfitting,
and allows higher learning rates.
The details of how it works are
beyond the scope of this video,
but it involves creating
trainable parameters
for the mean and standard deviation
of the values output
by the normalization layer.
I'll leave a link in the description,
if you want to learn more.
The second concept is residual blocks.
As neural network depth increases,
accuracy gets saturated
and then degrades rapidly.
Too many layers leads to
higher training error,
since gradients get
too small to be meaningful.
The solution is a skip connection,
which allows the input
to skip the entire layer
and get added to the output.
This allows gradients to propagate
through a very deep network,
and unlocks the full benefits
of deep learning.
This works much like a dry/wet knob
and effects processing.
It mixes the original signal back
into the effect.
Here's a visualization
of a Photoshop effect being applied,
and then added back
to the original image.
Again, if you want to learn more,
I'll leave a link in the description.
Here's the big picture of
the AlphaZero neural network.
It's made of building blocks,
so look at the overall design,
and we'll take a microscope
to each type of block.
At the top, the raw game data goes
into a simple convolutional layer.
Below that, we've got a tower of
40 residual convolutional layers.
The tower then feeds into a value head,
which outputs the expected value
of the state,
and a policy head which
outputs probabilities for
each possible action.
In other words, it's exactly
the same output
as vanilla actor critic architecture.
Now, let's take a look
one by one in each part.
First, let's see what the encoded
game state looks like
that's being passed in
there first layer,
specifically for the game of Go.
Chess and Shogi are
slightly different,
but the concepts are exactly the same.
The Go board is 19 by 19,
and so is input.
The current position of all of
black's pieces are encoded in the grid,
followed by identical grids
for the previous 7 time periods.
Then, we have white's current position
followed by the previous 7 time period
for white.
Finally, we've got the current
player's turn encoded on
a 19 by 19 grid.
All 1 if black is to play,
and all 0 if white is to play.
The result is a 19 by 19 by 17 stack,
which goes into the neural network.
Now, let's look at
the very first layer we hit,
the convolutional layer.
The input we just described passes
straight into a convolution
with 256 filters
and a 3x3 kernel.
If you don't fully understand
convolutions,
I'll link an excellent video
by Siraj in the description.
Next, we perform batch normalization
as described previously.
And, it passes through
a ReLu activation,
which effectively clips all
negative values to zero.
Now, we've got 40 stack
residual layers.
Inside each one is
the exact same thing,
so let's take a peek.
First up, we have
256 convolutional filters
with a 3x3 kernel as before.
Then, batch normalization,
ReLu activation,
another convolution,
more batch normalization,
and, finally, we have
the skip connection,
where the original input is added back
into the convolved output.
And, one more ReLu just for good luck.
Now, let's take a look at
the value head.
Input passes straight to one filter.
A one by one kernel convolution.
We do batch normalization.
It goes through a ReLu activation.
We have a fully connected layer
with 256 hidden neurons.
Another ReLu.
And a final, fully connected layer
with tanh activation
which outputs a value between -1 and 1
for the state being queried.
And, finally, we have the policy head
which outputs logit probabilities
for each possible move.
Input passes to 2 convolutional filters
with a one by one kernel.
Then, we do batch normalization.
Pass it through a ReLu
And, finally, through
a fully connected layer,
which outputs probabilities
for each square in the 19 by 19 grid
plus one additional option
for passing the turn.
And last, let's have a look at the loss function,
and the gradient descent method.
This is very similar to
how we trained our actor critic.
The loss function has
three elements,
the value loss, the policy loss,
and regularization.
Value loss is the mean squared error
between the value predicted
by the network
and the actual value calculated
through the Monte Carlo tree search.
Policy losses across entropy
between the probability is predicted
by the network
and those calculated through
Monte Carlo tree search.
If you're confused about this,
go back and study my policy gradients
math primer.
There's a link in the description
of my policy gradient methods video.
Last regularization helps
prevent overfitting
by adding a penalty as
a weights get bigger.
The equation for
L2 weight regularization loss
is c times a normal of theta squared.
In other words, this is the sum of
the squares of all the weights
in the network.
c is a parameter for controlling
the strength of the weight penalty.
Set to 10^-4 for
the AlphaZero paper.
And this is the final loss function.
z is the value of the state calculated
by Monte Carlo tree search.
v is the value predicted
by the network.
pi is a policy predict
and p are the actual probabilities
calculated by Monte Carlo tree search.
The momentum optimizer was used
with the momentum variable
being set to 0.9.
The learning rate
started out as 10^-2
and was annealed to 10^-4
after 600,000 iterations.
All right.
Now, that you've been firehose
with tons of theory,
it's time to take a look at some code.
You probably have enough information
to replicate AlphaZeroes results,
if you had thousands of dollars
in cloud computing credits
on your hands.
Well, it's scale it back a little bit,
and do something
you can get good results
training on your desktop GPU
over just a few days.
Let's use the AlphaZero algorithm
to build an AI
that can master the classic game
of Connect Four.
This is Colin Skow.
Stay tuned, because in the next video,
we're going to get our hands dirty.
And jump into some real-world code.
The Move 37 course is coming to an end,
so if you want to stay in touch,
Subscribe to my youtube channel,
Skowster the Geek.
See you again very soon.