Hello, world! It's Siraj.
The internet of things.
It's definitely a buzzword these days.
But, it's a real thing.
I'll demonstrate how to use
reinforcement learning
to optimize electricity consumption
amongst multiple devices
in a smart home.
Marc Andriessen's quote that
"Software is eating the world"
still rings true today.
More and more devices are
coming prepackaged
with internet access
that wouldn't normally be.
That includes:
smart salt shakers,
smart rectal thermometers,
smart mugs,
smart chairs,
the list goes on.
Because these devices
have a connection to the world wide web,
they can communicate with the outside world
and each other,
sharing information and
even learning from one another.
This internet of physical things is
becoming increasingly common
across the globe
whether it's a smart home,
a fleet of self-driving cars,
or a pipeline of assets.
As they are shipped across the globe,
having a web of
interconnected physical devices
has a huge range of use cases
in our modern world
for businesses and consumers.
But, a major concern regarding
these devices is
the amount of energy
they'll need to consume.
Silicon chips need electricity.
The more devices we have,
the higher our energy cost will be.
It turns out that we can use
reinforcement learning
to create a system
that will minimize our
electricity costs substantially.
This can apply to a
whole range of industries
where an interconnected system of devices
is required to perform a task.
Agriculture, manufacturing, and
even a personal home
which will be our demo.
Google recently used RL
to reduce the amount of energy.
They used in their data center
by up to 40 percent.
Just like a laptop generates heat.
Their massive racks of servers
generate a lot of heat.
But, too much heat can
damage the servers,
so a cooling system is necessary
to help maintain
a certain temperature.
Because it's such a
dynamic environment,
a learning system is required
to set that temperature.
A whole host of unforeseen scenarios
like changes in weather
and power outages can occur.
Also, humans interact
with the equipment
in unexpected ways regularly.
Probably doing the
floss dance on them.
And, each data center
has a unique architecture
and environment.
So, their system needed to
be able to adapt
to multiple unique environments.
Last week, we introduced
the fundamental way
of framing the reinforcement
learning problem,
where an agent is interacting
with an environment to maximize a reward.
The Markov decision process.
The goal of an agent is to learn a policy,
so it knows, given a state,
the best action to take
in order to maximize a reward.
In a complete Markov decision process,
where all of the environment
variables are known,
we can use dynamic programming
to learn an optimal policy.
But, what if we don't know
all the environment variables beforehand?
Give up!
No.
Then, it'd be considered
not model-based RL,
but model free RL.
In model free RL,
the first variable we miss
is a transition model.
So, we won't know
what's going to happen
after each action we take beforehand.
This tells us
the probabilities associated
with various state changes.
The second thing we miss is
the reward function
which gives the agent the reward
associated with a particular state beforehand.
So, when we don't know either of
these Markovian variables,
dynamic programming won't work.
We need to instead use
a different type of method
called Monte Carlo.
Monte Carlo methods are
a broad class of algorithms
that rely on repeated
random sampling
to obtain numerical results.
The keyword here is random.
Monte Carlo methods
make use of randomness
to solve problems,
which turns out to be very useful
in mathematics and physics.
Stanislaw Ulam invented it
in the late 1940s,
while working on a nuclear bomb
as part of the Manhattan Project.
Then, John von Neumann
decided he liked it,
and programmed a machine to do
those same calculations.
They decided to name
the code base Monte Carlo
as every super-secret project
should be named.
Ulam's uncle happened to be
losing lots of money
in the monte carlo casino
in Monaco.
So, that's why.
Uncle's...
In fact, DeepMind AlphaGo used
what's called
a Monte Carlo tree search
to help it play against
the reigning go champion
resulting in move 37.
More on that at the end of the course.
Monte Carlo techniques have
several advantages
over dynamic programming.
First, they allow for
learning optimal behavior
directly from interaction
with the environment
without needing the transition
or reward function defined beforehand.
Second, it's easy and
computationally efficient
to focus MC methods
on a small subset of the total states.
Third, MC can be used with simulations.
Let's say we have a home,
that consists of a bunch of
Internet of Things devices.
We've got a smart TV,
a smart fridge,
a smart dog,
and a smart giant server
in our room.
All of this equipment requires
a lot of electricity to run,
but it also requires cooling
or else my room would get too hot.
So, I have a cooling system.
Now, let's say that we have access to
our electricity usage logs,
thanks to partnering
with a data friendly provider.
Our smart thermostat can
set a temperature accordingly
depending on
the type of system we build.
We can imagine electricity flowing
into all of these devices
creating a closed loop system.
This constant stream of electricity data
can definitely be utilized.
It's giving us the electricity price,
cooling demand,
and electricity consumption as variables.
Using this,
we can construct
our Markov decision process.
The goal of our system is
to minimize our electricity bills.
More money for GPUs (?)
Our agent will perform an action
in this environment.
That action will be to either increase
or decrease the temperature
by one degree Celsius.
My fellow Americans,
most of this audience uses
the metric system.
The state then, that our agent can be in,
will be a measure of both:
how much cooling demand there is,
as well as, the price of electricity.
The reward can tell us whether
we are saving money or not
by switching states.
By calculating the total
electricity consumption,
multiplied by
the price of electricity,
and depending on
if that's greater
or less than what exists
at the time step before,
we know whether or not
that is a positive or negative reward.
There exists
an optimal policy here,
such that, if we were to
give it a state,
in this case, that would be
the cooling demand
and the electricity price,
it would know exactly
what temperature the thermostat
should be set at,
such that, we are optimally
saving money on electricity
by cooling our room
as much as necessary
when necessary.
Our adaptive real time reward
based system
needs to learn
this optimal policy.
Since we don't know
the reward function
or the transition function beforehand,
we have to compute
our rewards and transitions
as they happen in real time.
We'll want to use
a model free technique
like Monte Carlo
to learn the optimal policy.
The basic idea is to
calculate the value function
of each state backwards
with the reward received
after the end of the episode.
There has to be an ended, then
the task has to be
considered an episodic task
for us to use Monte Carlo.
In our case, we can say
that an episode lasts
a full eight hours,
while I'm away at my office
working diligently.
If we move from the initial state
to the terminal state
according to the given policy,
we'll receive a reward
at each time step.
We'll remember all of
those rewards,
and when we get to
the terminal state,
we'll loop back and
calculate the value function
of each state.
In the case that
there are multiple episodes,
then Monte Carlo just
averages all of the returns.
We know that the return is
the sum of the discounted reward.
In the context of Monte Carlo though,
we switch it up.
To obtain the state value function,
we take instead
the expectation of the returns,
not the sum.
We can define a state S
to be a discrete random variable,
which can assume all the stats
with a certain probability.
Every time our agent reaches a state,
it's like we are picking a value
for the random variable S.
For each state of each episode,
we can calculate the return
and store it in a list.
Repeating this process a lot
is guaranteed to converge
on the true state value function.
In Monte Carlo RL,
we are estimating the value function
for each state,
based on the return of each episode.
The more episodes
we take into account,
the more accurate or estimation will be.
Notice though, that
a possible problem could occur.
What if we visit the same state
twice in a single episode?
Well, there are actually
two types of Monte Carlo
policy evaluation:
first visit, and every visit.
We'll focus on first visit
in this video.
First visit only recognizes
the first visited state.
Every second visit does not count
the return for that state visit,
and the return is calculated
separately for each visit.
Monte Carlo includes randomness,
because when it updates
every episode
depending on where
it originated from,
it's a different result
depending on which action we take
in the same state.
Because it contains
these random elements,
Monte Carlo has a high variance.
When we graph a simulation of our agent
solving a problem,
we'll see that eventually.
The policy will converge,
and then our system will know
exactly what temperature
to set our room
based on the electricity
related variables.
There are different kinds of
Monte Carlo techniques
that can do all sorts of cool things.
But, we'll talk about those later on.
Three points to remember from this video.
In model free reinforcement learning,
as opposed to model based,
we don't know the reward function
and the transition function beforehand.
We have to learn them through experience.
A model free learning technique
called Monte Carlo
uses repeated random sampling
to obtain numerical results.
In first visit Monte Carlo,
the state value function is defined
as the average of the returns
following the agent's first visit to s
in a set of episodes.
Please subscribe for
more programming videos.
For now, I've got to
try a new sample.
Thanks for watching.