Streaming
In three,
two,
one,
go!
Event is started.
Stream has begun.
The world is here, and
ready for reinforcement learning.
I think we're live, great!
Hello, world! It's Siraj,
and welcome to my live stream.
In this live stream,
I'm going to attempt this Kaggle challenge,
called the "Two Sigma
Financial Modeling Challenge".
It's a hundred thousand dollars
worth of prize money.
I'm going to create an algorithm that's going to
hopefully get into the top fifty leaderboards.
We'll see how well it does,
but I want to just start off by saying
that the point of this video is first of all
to talk about some time
forecasting techniques.
For some reason,
in all the videos that I've made,
I haven't talked about time series forecasting
outside of the context of
deep neural networks,
but I will, in this video.
The other part of this video is for me to
show that reinforcement learning
can be used in the real world
in an applicable setting, and
This is part of Move 37,
so that's why I'm doing this.
How this video is going to be structured is
it's going to be an intro Q&A,
so I'm going to answer two questions,
so go ahead and start asking them now.
I'm going to go over a time series lecture,
brief Q&A,
exploratory data analysis
or EDA for our dataset,
brief Q&A,
and then reinforcement learning.
The point of this is to predict
a value.
Obviously, all machine learning is
about predicting a value, but
we're trying to predict a specific target value,
and I'll talk about that when we get to it.
Let me just start off by
answering two questions,
and then we'll get into the code.
Okay.
The first question is
Hi, everybody.
Thank you for being here.
The first question is
"can you suggest some
gesture recognition algorithms?".
Sure.
Right now, pose estimation
is the state of the art.
Go to use Tensorflow.js.
Probably, the easiest to use implementation
for pose estimation in the browser,
anybody can do it,
so that's the one to use.
So, that's the first one.
The next question out of two is
"what does it require to
create a bot like a human?".
Great, advanced question.
Now, I'm going to minimize this.
Hello, everybody.
So, that question.
A bot like a human.
That is AGI,
artificial general intelligence.
You know, the Turing test,
which hasn't really been passed yet.
That would be an open domain chatbot.
It would be trained on data
that is not a closed loop, but
just, you know, the entire Internet,
and this hasn't been solved,
but the best way forward
with that would be
I would say
using deep reinforcement learning
in the context of
of text data, and the web.
Having an open domain where
there's a cycle where
you're using reinforcement learning
where you're using a reward signal
to train a deep neural network
where it's searching the internet itself.
It's querying the Internet,
and it's building off of these queries.
It's using natural language processing
hence the deep neural network
to create abstractions
from the text data,
and then based on those abstractions
it's learning to maximize a reward
which would be to say
you know, you could frame it,
so that a human would say
yes/no binary, that this is
a good response or not.
Yeah, so that's kind of a research direction
that I'm thinking of
what hasn't been done,
but what would be cool for
human level chat bots
That's it for the Q&A.
Let's start talking about
time series analysis, because
In this dataset,
they're asking us to predict a target variable
based on the past
Okay? So...
Let's just talk about
time series analysis in general.
where we have two variables.
Let's start off with univariate,
a single variable,
time series analysis.
We have some price data.
Let's say this is for Bitcoin.
This is a Bitcoin price over a period of days.
Now, if we want to forecast
the price for the next day,
how do we do that?
This is a time series where
the variables depend on the time.
What the values are
what their target variables are
are completely dependent
on that time step.
That's what makes it different
from a regular dataset.
A time series dataset depends on the time.
What we would do here is
the naive approch.
Let's just start off with a naive approch.
Where we say,
What this next datapoint
is going to be in this graph?
Is going to be
the target variable?
That's it.
So we are just going to say that
the predicted variable, and here is the equation,
is going to be the variable
from the previous time step.
That's it.
Right? That's the equation right there.
We would call this the naive approch.
So what happens is
when we have a dataset like this
where just imagine
the entire thing is one dataset
and we have split it into
training and testing data
where we say, okay,
this is the entire training dataset.
Now, based on this last datapoint,
predict the next point.
What it's going to say
Well, based on this one,
let me just do that again,
because that's our variable.
That's our equation,
or forecast model.
It'll do that
again and again and again.
What happens is,
it's just a straight line.
So this is a very bad approach.
This is the naive approach.
Let's see how
we can improve on this.
How would we improve?
Well,
check out this graph.
It's got volatility.
it's going up, it's going down.
But notice that there is an average line.
You can imagine that
there is this average line.
The line of best fit, you could call,
where it is the average between
the ups and the downs.
We could draw it mentally
through this model.
And so if we do that,
if we do that,
then we can make the assumption
that the next price is going to be
the average of all the prices
that came before it.
So if we have that
sequence of values of
all of those y values,
The y values are right here on this axis.
The x values are here, the days.
Then, we could use this equation.
Now, don't be afraid about
the fact that we are using
a little bit of math here
what this says is the target variable,
which we can call y hat,
the one we want to predict,
is going to be equal to
the sum.
This is sigma notation.
This greek E looking letter.
The sum of all of those variables
that came before it
divided by
the total number of them, x.
From i to x, where x is
the number of variables
add them all up.
That's what sigma notation means,
and then divide by the number of them.
That's the average, and that's our prediction.
So if we do that,
this is what our line
is going to look like.
Okay?
So it's saying,
based on this last datapoint right here
What's going to be the next one?
Well, it's not going to be up here.
It's going to be down here.
Because we're taking into account
all of those datapoints from
the very very beginning
to the very end.
But notice that this is not ideal, either.
We need something that's
going to be better than that.
So how do we improve on that?
Well, we would use a different technique,
called the "moving average".
What the moving average does is, it says
The points at the very beginning,
and the points near the end,
these are completely different directions.
So let's only consider the points
immediately before our forecasts,
our target variable, that we want to predict.
So we'll have a window,
and we'll just average those.
We'll leave out the beginning,
What that equation looks like is this,
where y hat, the predictor variable,
is going to be
the sum of all of those,
that all of those values that
came before our target variable,
up to a certain threshold,
which we define as p,
Say, the previous five,
or the previous six variables.
divided by the total number of them.
That's the average.
If we do that,
Now, notice, there's a little bit.
It's getting better, our prediction.
Right? It looks like this.
Now, how can we improve on this?
Notice I'm going through
a lot of techniques very fast.
So slow me down,
if you feel like it's too fast.
Well,
one way we can improve that
is by using a technique,
called "simple exponential smoothing".
What that means is,
you know,
let's take into account
all of those variables.
Because, clearly, all of them matter.
But let's weight them differently.
Let's weight them differently,
where we say
the variables that came
immediately preceding
for our predictor, our target variable,
will weigh them more than the variables
that came at the very beginning.
Because these matter more.
So, how do we do that mathematically?
Here's how.
We take this constant value,
which we're going to call alpha.
And we do the same thing,
where we're adding them all up.
But we're multiplying it
by this constant value.
And squared, cubed,
to the fourth, to the fifth.
Notice this trend here of
exponentially increasing.
So this is called
"simple exponential smoothing".
Okay.
What this means is that
these variables
are going to be weighted differently.
Now, here's a question for you.
I'm very excited.
I'll be very impressed,
if someone can answer this question.
What does this formula look like
that we already know about
from reinforcement learning literature.
Such rich literature,
what does this formula look like?
If anybody can answer that,
I'm going to be very impressed
Let me keep going though.
Okay?
Ready?
Okay,
it looks very similar
to the discount factor
from reinforcement learning.
So, in the reinforcement learning context,
We have an agent.
It acts in an environment.
It's making an action,
and it receives an observation
of the next state.
In order to maximize reward,
how do we maximize reward?
Well, here's how we calculate reward
at every time step we can predict
what the reward will be
for being in a specific state
up to our end state, the terminal state.
We'll add up all those rewards,
multiplied by a constant factor,
called the discount factor.
We are weighting those rewards
in order of
the rewards that came
immediately previously.
We're weighing them more.
We're saying that they're more important,
than the rewards that came
at the very very beginning.
That's the discount factor.
Yeah. Wow, actually people got that.
I'm very impressed.
Good job, guys.
Very good.
So, let's keep improving here.
By the way, the reason
I wanted to say that is because
is to just give you some intuition
behind reinforcement learning.
It's a framework for viewing the world,
and how intelligent agents
interact in the world.
It's not the actual mathematics of
intelligence of pattern recognition,
but it's more about framing
these pattern recognition networks
in the context of a dynamic world
that adapts to that intelligent agent.
More on that at the end.
Holt was a mathematician in 1964,
I think was the year.
who invented a linear trend model.
Where he said,
You know what?
This idea of single exponential smoothing,
it works, it's fine.
However,
let's improve on that,
because it doesn't take into account
the idea of a trend.
A trend is a general direction,
that we see that
a graph is moving in.
The way to mathematically
define a trend,
as holt suggested in his
linear trend model,
would be to create
a forecast equation,
that consists of
two other equations.
So, we have a level equation,
and then we have
a trend equation.
We use both of those equations
to compute the final,
forecast equation.
So, it's l + hb,
where l is the level equation,
and b is a trend location.
We have two constant factors.
We have alpha, and we have beta.
They're both different, and
we can tune them accordingly.
The level equation is the same idea
of exponential smoothing,
but applied to both the level,
the average value in
the series, and the trend
If we do that,
then notice our graph's forecast
is getting much better.
Now, there's one more technique
I want to talk about.
This is an improvement,
that Holt made
to that linear trend model.
We'll start coding in a second.
It's called his winter seasonal method.
There's another
concept in forecasting,
called seasonality,
where in a set of data
there's going to be seasons.
In any kind of time series data,
there's going to be
some kind of seasonal,
not any, but most of them, real-world.
There's going to be some
seasonality, where
There's going be some kind of
predictable up,
and some predictable downs.
Let's say, for retail stores,
there's going to be more people
buying toys in December,
because of Christmas
in a lot of Western countries,
or you know wherever.
Or, there's going to be
some kind of trend
in the seasonal direction,
for stock markets as well.
Based on this,
this is what's happening,
here's how the markets going to go.
So, in order to mathematically
define seasonality,
we have now three equations.
We're adding on to what we had before.
Again, we're using our level.
We're using our trend.
And now, we add a third equation,
which is the seasonal equation,
where the level equation shows
the weighted average
between the seasonally
adjusted observation,
and the non-seasonal
forecast for time, T.
The trend equation is
the same as Holt's linear method,
and the seasonal equation shows
the weighted average,
between the current seasonal index
and the seasonal index
of the same season last year.
Each of these equations is
interdependent on each other.
What happens when we do that is,
Now, we are getting somewhere.
Check out this this graph.
It's a much better graph, right?
That's the idea of seasonality.
That's for the case of
univariate time series.
If we have multivariate time series,
that's multiple input data for
whatever the
multiple predictor variables
for whatever our target variable
is going to be,
which is the case for our
two sigma financial modelling contest.
Then, we're going to use a model
that is very similar to
Holt's winter seasonal method.
That's taking into account.
The level, the trend, the seasonality,
right to make the forecast.
But, it's also finding
linear interdependencies
between these
predictor variables.
It's the same idea of
multiple equations,
that are relating to each other,
in a way that
once they relate to each other,
we can create a graph.
Some popular models for that are
ARIMA, ARIMAX, etc.
I'll make a dedicated video
on those, because
you really need to make
a dedicated video on those, and
Or, we could treat this
as a supervised problem, as
many people had done,
where we use the power of
LSTM networks.
To then, treat it as
a supervised problem, where we say
the predictor variable,
let's say, pollution.
That's the...
Sorry, the target.
The target variable is going to be
the result of the predictor variables,
the temperature,
the human waste use amount, etc.
So, there's a mapping
between those two.
The reason we use LSTM networks,
long short-term memory
neural networks,
is because they take into account
long term sequence data,
and they store memory
in a way that is
beneficial to sequential data
which is the case of
time series data.
That's why we've seen
a lot of LSTM networks
being used in time series data.
Let's get into some EDA.
Like I said, I'm going to
answer some questions now.
All right,
so what are some questions?
Okay.
What's out of focus?
I know it is.
Okay.
When did you start programming?
I started programming...
You know, that's a hard question,
because I've been,
I used to like,
I guess the,
I guess the earliest time
that I started programming was
It's almost embarrassing
to say, but like
like modifying Halo 2
when I was
I think 13 or 14.
So, that was a while ago.
But, I wasn't even programming.
I was more like downloading scripts,
and just like
hacking it and stuff.
So, it's been a while,
but really seriously programming
probably a couple years,
a couple years.
Okay, who is paying you?
Nobody's paying me.
I mean YouTube ads
are paying me.
Patreon, you guys
To do this,
nobody's paying me.
Nobody's paying me.
Kaggle,
nobody's paying me.
I would have to say that
if somebody was paying.
Which is the best book for RL?
Sutton and Bartow have the Bible of RL,
which is called
"an introduction to reinforcement learning".
Find it on the Internet.
It's all available for free.
Last question is,
I'm going to
get a haircut, for sure.
Will you attend...
I will.
Do time series data
definitely depends on other factors?
It depends on a lot of factors,
if there's multiple variables.
Okay?
Okay.
Now, to the dataset,
let's go ahead and do this.
So first of all, now the dataset is
in the video description.
So check the video description.
We're going to do this
in Google Collab together.
We're ready for our
exploratory data analysis step.
What I did was...
By the way, with Google Collab
with these two lines, you can mount
whatever dataset you want
into Google Collab, and then
call it directly.
So, what I did was, I downloaded it.
It's an h5 file.
Uploaded it to my Google Drive,
and then called it
with this
these two lines of code.
Very simple.
Thank you, Google Collab,
for making it much easier to do.
Alright, so let's get into this code.
Our first step
is going to be to list out our dataset.
We have this dataset,
or I have this dataset
in my Google Drive.
And, I have a link for you
in the video description.
I just want to see, if it's there.
Okay, good. It's there.
That was it.
Once I've seen that it's there,
now I'm going to convert it
into a pandas dataframe.
But, before that I've got to
import this dependency,
or install this dependency, called tables.
That's going to let me do that.
Now, we can import pandas,
our handy-dandy data
pre-processing Python library.
To then,
to then say,
let's import this dataset
that train.h5.
Okay, recursively,
and we're going to
import it as train.
That's what we're going to call it.
Then, we're going to say,
our dataframe is going to be train.get,
and then we'll call it by
its name train, and that's it.
And hopefully...
Good
So, now we have it as a dataframe.
Now, we can see how big is our dataset.
How big is this thing?
We got to check it out.
This thing is
massive.
It is over 1.7 million datapoints,
which is big.
Let's examine this dataset.
Just to see the head, just of
the first few variables.
Okay, so
here's our dataset.
We have an id.
We have a timestamp,
which is going to be a different time.
These are all of our predictor variables.
What do these mean?
And...
There's like more than 40 to
44 variables,
and then we have ys.
y is our predictor variable.
In this competition,
two sigma, what they did was,
they said,
These are a bunch of
financial instruments.
Financial instruments are like
derivatives, bonds, mortgages,
stocks, assets,
all of these different types of
financial instruments.
but they anonymize them.
So, we're calling them just
technical_41, technical_42.
And then, we have a predictor variable.
What is this predictor variable?
They didn't reveal to us,
but we can think of it as a price.
Let's just think of it as
a price in a trend,
and this price for
this asset is dependent
on all these other anonymized
financial instruments.
Based on all of these
financial instruments,
can we predict the price?
For whatever this is.
Let's just say, it's a stock
for this case.
Okay?
Let's keep going here.
Our next step is to say,
We'll call them labels.
So, y is going to be labels.
How many labels, and how many
values do we have.
So, what we're going to do is
we're going to list them both
by creating two matrices,
and saying
the labels
are going to be appended
by the number of columns that we have.
The values are going to be
appended by
the number of
non-empty variables we have.
And then, we'll print out
all of those columns,
and all of those values
starting from
the very beginning.
All right.
Oh, right.
df
Let's see if that works.
Good, okay.
These are all of our variables,
all of our values,
or all of our labels and values.
Okay, so
just like that.
So now, we want to see how much
we have to do some data cleaning.
How much missing data do we have?
So now, we can use matplotlib.
To see just how much
missing data we have.
Because, we probably have a lot.
So, plt as our matplotlib,
and then we'll say,
We'll use this inline.
Call, to say that
we want to be able to
show a matplotlib graph
inside of the browser.
We're going to create a matplotlib graph,
and we're going to say that
it's going to contain
a
figure size.
That's going to be between
12 and 50, so we'll
we'll keep it
small, relatively small,
and we're going to start
from those labels,
which I named an ind.
And, connect to those labels.
We have all of our values.
And, I'm going to color them.
I'm going to label them y.
So, in my graph,
it's going to say y.
And now, we can say,
let's say,
set the y ticks,
so these are going to be
the intervals between these variables
to
Let's say, it's gonna be half of the width
that I defined for which is 0.9,
because those values we saw before
they seem to be
in that range.
So now, we'll say,
y ticks.
And, let me just
do that again y ticks.
tick labels,
so
that's the labels,
and then we have
our other
line which is our horizontal line.
Oh, I'm going to name it
the other line horizontal,
and we're going to have,
That's for y.
and then count of missing values.
That's what we're looking for
the count of missing values.
xlabel
and
one more which is
our title for our graph.
Number of
missing values in each column.
Okay, that's it.
And, show the plot.
Okay, let's see.
Of course.
Invalid syntax.
ax.
ax.set
yticks
ind
+
width
just like that
ind
np is not defined.
Right.
Is it really not defined?
I didn't import numpy up there?
Okay, fine.
as np
Okay...
figsize, right.
So, sometimes you just got to
deal with these
errors...
Nice.
Looks like we've got quite a lot of
missing values in our data
And so, you know,
if we could, we could just
clean them all out, but
this is a good step to
Wow, fundamental_61 has
a lot of missing values.
There's a lot of missing values
in this data.
So, that's what we wanted to do.
Just to see that.
Let's just show one more pretty graph.
It's a rainbow graph.
We can use the other plotting library,
called Seabourn to do this.
It's just one more very simple graph.
And so, we'll say...
and I'll take questions
right after
number 8 here.
How many people
do we have in here?
Okay.
Okay, cool.
So...
That's it for this.
Now, we can see
at each timestep,
We want to see at each time step
what the data looks like.
We'll say,
how much of each
predictor variable
do we have at each time step?
Okay, so now,
we can see that.
Cool.
Okay, that's the count
for each versus the time step.
There's more and more it's going up
the trend of the data is going up.
That's just one thing to know.
It's a linear trend upwards,
as time goes on.
Okay.
Lastly, we'll just add one line of code,
and we're done with this EDA part.
How many unique assets
do we have in total?
And, that's...
prints the length of df.id.unique().
Let's answer some questions,
then I'll talk about
reinforcement learning.
Can we use RNN with LSTM
to predict these scenarios?
Yes, you can like
I mentioned before.
Deep reinforcement learning
is the cutting edge for that.
Two,
Phillip asked,
Why not use pandas dataframe methods
to call the columns
instead of using loops?
Phillip, that's a totally valid question.
We could have done that.
Lastly, one more question.
What is your opinion of...
Nah, that's no...
How deep do you need to know
math for reinforcement learning?
That's a great question.
Compared to
supervised and
unsupervised learning,
it is more necessary
to know the math behind it,
because,
that ecosystem is not as developed
as a supervised learning ecosystem.
While we can use OpenAI Gym
to do a simple random policy
for an agent inside of a game,
if you want to do
anything more complex,
deep Q, if you really want to
understand these algorithms,
then yes.
You're going need to know
how, what the idea behind
policy functions are,
and the idea behind value functions
both for a state and an action.
You're going to need to know
how the bellman equation works.
And, that's really what
it what it comes down to.
Understand the bellman equation,
and everything else will follow.
There's four of them actually,
and I will continue to talk about them.
But, let's continue going here.
That's it for my Q&A.
Now, to RL.
Right. So, that's our EDA.
Now for RL.
How do we use reinforcement learning
in time series data?
In reinforcement learning,
there is an agent
that is acting on the outside world.
It is observing the effects
of the environment,
and it's learning how to
improve its behavior.
That's why we see it being
used so often in games.
But, in contrast,
a time series forecast
is a setting where
there is a passive observer,
so the agent is passively observing
the data set.
It's not really interacting with
the environments, because
the environment is
not reacting to the agent.
It is a one way
action, right?
Whereas in a game world,
for example, like Hart Pole,
where the where the pole is
trying to balance itself.
If the agents action in a given state
is to move to the left,
then the environment,
the platform that its balancing on
will then move its reacting.
So, in a real world,
how do we use this?
What is a system that adapts
to changes that
an agent, an AI makes?
Well...
The stock market could be one where
a state will change, because
the state is the account balance.
If you have an account balance
when an agent makes an action
like buy sell or hold,
the balance will change.
Or, if we want to get more meta,
then the
the entire stock market will change.
If an agent makes a trade,
then the market will change.
That is a reactive environment.
What is another reactive environment?
Electricity grids,
sensor networks,
interconnected routing grids of data
of connections.
Any kind of system that adapts
an adaptive system that reacts
to an agent interacting with
that environment
is a use case for
reinforcement learning.
So, a static data set is
not necessarily
a reinforcement learning scenario.
How do we solve this?
Because there are a bunch of
companies out there
that have these systems.
Like Google, for example,
they use reinforcement learning
to improve the
They use it to improve
the quality of their
power usage in their
giant data center.
They reduce their cooling bill.
I think it was 40%, and
even more after that
So, there are companies out there.
Electricity companies,
power utility companies,
public works companies,
that have these systems
that need to be optimized,
but they don't.
They have these real-time datasets
meters that are happening in real time.
What they need then is
a reinforcement learning solution.
But, right now,
and here's a startup idea
I want to get to you guys.
This stream is going up and down.
Like there were 200 people here.
Now, there's 600 people here.
This is crazy by the way.
Where was I?
This is a call to action for startups,
because I see a real need here.
Here's a pain point, where
there are companies that need
a reinforcement learning
solution to help optimize
their profits for their systems.
There are data scientists
out there, that
that want to use
reinforcement learning to then
solve these systems.
So what there needs to be
is an intermediary,
that offers a simulation as a service.
What these simulation is
the service companies do,
or startups will do
is they'll approach
and here's how I would do it
I would approach one of these
companies and say,
I understand reinforcement learning.
I understand that we can offer you
a 30% reduction in your costs,
if you give us access to
your real-time API.
And, we'll create a
simulated environment
based on that.
Then, we will give it to say,
Kaggle
to then allow their
data scientists to
create RL algorithms.
So, there is an intermediary step here.
Now, Kaggle can do this themselves.
They have thought about this.
Who knows what's going to
happen there? But,
this is an idea that time has come.
More and more people are
getting interested
in reinforcement learning.
There needs to be more
simulated real world,
not game world,
environments out there.
That's my suggestion.
Hopefully, you understand
the difference here
between time series forecasting
and reinforcement learning
from what I've said so far,
and why there's a need for it,
and how we can apply
reinforcement learning
to time series.
If there is some
reactive component
to the data set itself,
it can't just be a static dataset.
It has to be a real-time API.
Okay, so there is a possibility
that we're going to see
more of that in the future.
Now,
what I did find though
what I did find was a library.
The closest thing on Kaggle
to
to this idea of
reinforcement learning
was created by this guy,
and it's called the Kaggle gym.
What he did was
he framed
he framed the reinforcement
learning problem
he framed the
not the reinforcement learning
two sigma problem
of predicting the target variable
as a reinforcement
learning problem
as a Markov decision process.
What I think is
this was the pioneering step
in saying...
Let's create a simulation of a dataset,
and then solve the datasets
and then solve the dataset
in the context of a simulated setting.
He created this library
called Kaggle gym.
Which takes that library
and what I've done is
I've pasted it in this library here,
and we're gonna talk about it,
and then we're gonna use it.
We're going to use that
Kaggle gym library
to solve this problem.
Little refresher here.
In reinforcement learning,
we have a Markov decision process.
Where we have an agents,
it performs a set of actions
in a given state
to maximize reward.
The action that it takes given a state
is considered the policy.
So, a policies suggest
it's a function
that says given this state.
And, given this action,
Oh, no. Given this state,
what's the best action to take.
That's how a policy works.
There's two other functions here.
That are a part of
a Markov decision process.
The transition probability
that says what is
the next likely state
to go in if you take an action
in this given state.
And, a reward function
that's going to help the agent
maximize what reward it receives
for taking a given action.
This can be learned over time,
and that would be
considered Q learning.
That would be considered
a model free method.
These two functions
could be learned over time,
or they can be given to us,
or beforehand,
in which case, this will be a complete
Markov decision process.
But in the real world,
we will never, almost never
have a complete
Markov decision process
We will almost always
have a partially observable
Markov decision process.
What that means is that
we won't have these
transition probabilities.
We won't have this reward function.
We'll have to learn them.
Or,
we could just avoid those functions,
and learn what's called
Q function directly.
Let me talk about that at the end.
Okay, I just wanted to introduce
the idea of a Markov
decision process,
before we get into this code.
In this Kaggle gym environment
that Frans Slothoubers suggested,
we have an R score.
So, what Kaggle suggested
was that
What kaggle suggested
Let me just go back.
was that the data
we evaluate the scores
using this equation right here.
Okay, let me make this bigger.
This
is called the R score.
The R score is
1 minus
the difference between
the target, and the
predicted variable squared,
the sum of all of them,
divided by
the predicted variable minus
What was u again?
This constant value u.
It's not called u.
It's called... forgetting the...
name of it
but this constant value.
and one minus that
and that's R squared.
And then, we can derive R
from R squared
by saying R equals
sign of R squared times
the square root of the absolute value
of R squared
and that's going to give us R
and that's going to be our
We can consider that a loss function,
because it's going to give us one scalar
it's going to give us a scalar value,
which we can use to measure
how good are our
our predicted variable is
our predicted target is.
Then, based on that R score,
we can see what the leaderboard says.
We can see what everybody's R score is here.
The highest one was 0.02.
We'll see what we can get
using this Kaggle gym library
that was created before.
Let me answer any other questions.
Mu! Yes, thank you very much.
mu(μ), alpha(α), theta(θ)
I was in mu, alpha, theta in high school.
How can I forget mu!
Okay.
How do i start the basics?
Move 37 is my course.
It's all on YouTube for free.
Check it out.
Right.
miu
Alright.
Great, guys. Thank you.
What is this?
Let me start off with this.
The R score,
this function is just the
programmatic version
of the equation that
I've just showed.
That's it.
That's how we're going to compute it.
Let me go through this.
Inside of this Kaggle gym environment,
we have an observation.
What the observation is
it is our training
it is our predicted variable
what we want to predict.
And, our...
It is our...
It is the variable that
we are predicting.
So, the predicted variable,
and the target variable.
what is already there
because we already have
those targets or labels.
We can call them labels. right?
So, labels.
Man, I'm sweating today.
Yes!
Okay.
We can call them labels.
Inside of our environment,
Inside of this environment,
and in our environment, what is it?
Our environment is
our static dataset.
We'll split it up into
training and testing data.
Here's the step function.
This is basically recreating that
open AI gym environment,
or an agent takes a step,
the parameter is the action that it takes.
It receives an observation and a reward.
In this very naive implementation,
how it's computed
how the R score is computed
is just by saying that
the predicted variable is
only going to be
the variable from
the previous time step.
We could do that, actually.
We could choose our own policy
based on this.
But, what inside of this alone
all it's saying is
This is really the key right here
like this part right here.
The reward for taking a step
in this environment is going to be
the R score of our
predicted variable
and our target.
That's our reward and
we return that
as well as an observation,
which is going to be
the values of both
as we saw before,
a boolean that says
done or not,
and an info which is
a logging variable.
Based on that, we can create a policy.
Let's write one
using this variable.
The reason I pasted it all is
because this could be its own Python file.
KaggleGym.py
Let's test this out.
We'll say
Let's create our own agent
environment loop.
we'll define our own policy,
and then based on that,
we'll try to improve it.
Inside of this test function, will say
go ahead and create
the environment using make,
which is the function
that I just defined,
get the initial observation
which is going to be
our variables that we
defined before.
We'll print them out,
so we can see them
just for logging purposes.
What is the observation of
both the target
and of the training data
or the predicted value.
Based on both of those,
we'll create our training loop.
This is the agent environment loop
based on that.
So, what we'll say is
while true,
Here's the loop begins.
The target value is going to be
the initial observation.
We'll choose some starting point
to just start from.
Like, what is the predictor variable
that we want to start from?
We'll just say...
And then...
observation
What are we going to get returned
when we take a step.
I'll continue to explain this guys.
Let me just write this out.
I'm not done explaining this.
This is the class that
we just talked about.
It's going to return
all three of these things
based on the action
which is the target we take.
And, if we're done,
break, we're done
with the loop.
Else,
Now, what do we do
with the rewards?
We can choose any policy.
Here is where we actually show
what that policy is going to be.
What I'm going to do it
as you're seeing right now is,
I'm going to print out three variables,
and then I'm done.
I'm going to print out the info.
I'm going to print out
the amount of rewards.
the first few rewards.
0 through 15.
Okay, so that's that.
Invalid syntax for make?
All right.
Environment
equals make.
And then, I'll test it out.
All I do is just run tests.
And that's gonna give us,
What?
Environment is not defined?
Did i, really?
No, it is.
Check this out.
Right.
And then,
Yep.
Oh, okay.
Observation is not defined.
Line 9.
Obser...
...vation.
Rewards is not defined.
rewards.append
Oh, rewards.
Okay.
Okay, let me answer some
questions now.
Because, we're definitely going to
have some questions here.
Okay.
Oh, break.
How did this not catch it?
Okay, gotcha.
Let me answer some questions here.
Thank you.
Let's see what we get here.
So, our public score
is going to be 0.017.
Compared to...
So, we're like #43.
Guess what this
Okay, so guess what?
Here's our policy.
Here's our policy right here.
All we're saying,
This is a naive method,
but in the context of
a Markov decision process.
That's it.
The basic idea here is
that we framed this as
a Markov decision process,
where an agent is taking action
in an environment
to move from one state
to the next state.
And, we're trying to maximize reward.
The policy to choose
that action is going to be
the variable that we
want to predict
is going to be the variable
from the last time step.
To compute the how good it is
we're just going to
find the difference
between the predicted
and the actual variable.
So, it's going to be
the variable in t-1 and t.
That's it.
We could have done this
in one line of code.
However,
In the context of a Markov decision
process which we have here,
we could then add to it
by creating another policy,
by creating a better policy,
that's going to improve on this.
It's like what would
be an example
Q learning
Okay? So, Q learning
where
an agent is taking
an action given a state
in order to maximize a reward,
and we are computing
this Q table
which is a giant matrix of
possible actions that we can take
in any given state.
Then, we're going to optimally
choose what those actions will be
by iteratively updating
the cue table
using what's called
the bellman equation.
What the bellman equation does
it relates one state to another.
If we can relate any one state
in an environment
to another state,
then we can compute
those variables
that are different between them.
Like, the state value function,
and the action value function.
Using those, we can compute
an optimal policy.
That's how we could improve on this.
However, like I said before,
we need an environment
that's going to be reactive.
This is also just to show that
you don't necessarily
have to have the greatest
cutting edge algorithm
in the world to place well
to on a challenge, or to do well in general
in machine learning.
Sometimes linear regression can work better
than a deep neural network,
if your data set is small,
or for a variety of reasons.
My point is that
we placed using this
very simple methodology.
Obviously, it's a very naive method.
But, I wanted to really sneak in
a lecture on reinforcement learning
on Q learning
on the difference betwee
time series forecasting
and reinforcement learning into this
problem of this Kaggle challenge.
This was the the most...
This specific challenge wa
the most RL friendly challenge
that's available on Kaggle right now.
And like I've said,
this is a great opportunity
for aspiring data scientists out there
to create a service
that creates simulated environments
that can be offered
to real-world companies
and to create a business out of that.
I see a real need for that
that could be
a use case for this.
I'll answer two more questions.
I actually have a great Q learning video
coming out this weekend.
I'm going to have some great links
for you in the video description.
The datasets in the video description.
Let me
do a rap.
So, just say a
just say a
a topic and
I'll do a free-style rap
on the topic, before I end
this live stream.
My favorite AI company is
School of AI.
We're actually a nonprofit organization,
and it is the adventure
of a lifetime,
and it is a story
that's going to be told
decades from now,
and it's not even about me.
It's about the deans.
It's about the people running this.
Really, it's a family,
the students, the wizards,
were all a family,
the people watching this.
We are all a family, if you are here
at the end of this live stream.
You are a dedicated data scientist
who cares
or AI researcher who cares
about the future of AI
and using it
to solve real-world problems.
That's our mission, our values.
Open AI.
No, I want to do a different one.
Chatbot.
Okay.
(beat starts)
Okay, here we go.
There's always a little tag
at the beginning.
♪ I've tried to use a chatbot ♪
♪ I've tried to make matplotlib ♪
♪ plot it out with the graph ♪
♪ but you can't because it's text data ♪
♪ man you gotta use math ♪
♪ I don't know what you're using man ♪
♪ you're out of class ♪
♪ you gotta take a chatbot ♪
♪ and visualize it ♪
♪ in a way that people can realize it ♪
♪ it's okay let me show you ♪
♪ instead of matplotlib ♪
♪ let's use something else like I call it ♪
♪ matplotjive ♪
♪ it's a new library ♪
♪ I've just invented it ♪
♪ it's made for chatbots ♪
♪ to visualize in the browser ♪
♪ it's like a laptop ♪
♪ it runs on anything ♪
♪ browser, in the cloud, GPU, CPU, TPU ♪
♪ I don't care ♪
♪ that's it for you ♪
All right, that's it.
That's it for the rap.
Thank you guys for showing up.
I hope I made this
enjoyable for you.
time series forecasting, RL,
Markov decision precesses
and the accessibility of
Kaggle as a way to
to earn a passive income,
and a way to hone your
skills as a data scientist.
These are all the things that
I hope you've learned in this live stream
I love you guys.
We're about to hit 500,000 subscribers,
so I can't wait. Tell all your friends.
We want to grow this community
as fast as possible.
So, thank you, guys.
I love you.
And, thanks for watching.
For now, I've got to go.
Work on school of AI stuff.
So, yeah. Thanks for watching.