Move 37; it's finally here.
Hello world! It's Siraj.
I've been teaching a course called
"Move 37" for the past ten weeks
I wanted to culminate it all
every RL technique we've talked about
with this one video.
I'm gonna explain what Move 37 is,
and three reasons why it's so significant for our future,
in terms of human jobs, health, and lifestyle.
The Go board game is very popular
in large parts of Asia;
it's very old and some players have
dedicated their entire lives to mastering it.
When polled, most AI researchers believed
it would take several decades for
computers to reach the standard
of a human expert player.
It's a very challenging game,
more potential board positions
than there are atoms in the universe.
A player has to learn how to recognize
abstract patterns in hundreds of pieces
placed across the board,
and even experts have a hard time explaining
why a particular move is
either benificial, or problematic.
So when DeepMind's AI program,
called AlphaGo Zero,
beat the world champion at Go
much earlier than expected,
history was made.
Starting with the training set
of recorded games
that contained over 30 million moves
made by expert Go players,
the AlphaGo Zero algorithm used a model
proven to be able to learn
from image data directly
called a Convolutional Neural Network.
It was fed a series of game states as input
meaning the positions on the board.
The network learned how to
predict the next move,
and learned to predict the outcome from
different arrangements on the board.
Since Go has so many potential moves,
a brute force search would take way too long;
even longer than it'll take Apple to release
an augmented reality device.
So instead, the convolutional network
was deployed
in the context of a search algorithm
called a Monte Carlo Tree Search.
This tree search was used to initially explore
many possible moves on the board,
then focus that exploration over time
as certain moves were found to be
more likely to lead to wins
than others.
AlphaGo used the neural network
to both predict moves to help guide
which branches of the game tree to search,
and it used it to evaluate the positions
it encountered during its search.
This allowed it to intelligently
search upcoming moves,
and ultimately beat
the world champion at the game.
But even more important than AlphaGo's win
was one moment during the game;
the moment that caused
Lee Sedol to leave the room.
AlphaGo played this move,
which I wanna hear more about in a second, but,
Uh... Lee has left the room.
He left the room after that move.
It was a move that seemed terrible
to everyone who saw it.
But it turned out that Move 37
was an incredible move to play,
and it was instrumental
in helping AlphaGo win the game.
Somehow, a computer program knew something
about the game that we didn't.
Somehow, it's intuition was both different
and better, than human intuition.
One of the players, Fan Hui, said:
AI thinks you're beautiful too, Fan. *winks*
Move 37 offered us a glimpse at
what an intelligence looks like
that thinks differently than we do,
but is still very much capable of
accomplishing tasks.
Interestingly, Lee played his own move
in a later game with AlphaGo,
since they were playing through a series of them,
which helped him win one of the games.
Move 78, called the Divine Move,
Brillaint Tesuji by some.
The designers of AlphaGo called it
a "one in ten-thousands move", because
AlphaGo calculated that there was
a probability of 1 out of 10,000
that a human would play that move.
Lee's Move 78 caused AlphaGo to make
sub-optimal decisions in the next round.
Lee learned that AlphaGo was superior
at playing the right moves
to optimize for small gains,
but it could fail in extreme situations
where the gain of points in one move
would be more important.
This was an example of
intelligence augmentation:
Better designed algorithms
lead to better performances,
and better performances help humans
make better decisions.
Humans who make better decisions
can create environments where
algorithms fail; i.e. "divine moves",
and learning about these failures
helps us design better algorithms.
The AlphaGo algorithm influence
Lee's gameplay, and vice versa.
We can work together
with this machine intelligence
in many different ways,
to further extend our capabilities
across every industry.
This kind of technology can help us
achieve goals that we could not do alone,
and I'll outline the three biggest ones.
The first is healthcare;
cancer, Alzheimer's, and a host of other
major diseases plague humanity,
many die every year because
our best scientists
haven't been able to find a cure.
In the USA, the path to develop a new medicine
takes at least ten years on average,
and costs an average of $2.6 billion US dollars.
And less than 12% of the candidate medicines
that make it into phase 1 clinical trials
are approved by the FDA.
There are billions of possible lead molecules
that could be used as potential cures,
so a scientist has to use their intuition
to pick one that would most likely
have the desired properties
for curing the disease in question.
The process of synthesizing and
testing a single new molecule in a lab
could cost thousands or
tens of thousands of dollars,
so the early stage guessing process
is really important.
We can use AI to help generate
a potential molecular structure,
say using a model like
Generative Adversarial Networks,
which have shown a lot of promise
generating different types of useful data.
In these dueling networks,
where one progressively
becomes a better generator
by trying to fool the other into thinking
what it's generated is real
through a feedback loop,
feeding in vast quantities of molecular data
that no human could process all at once
could result in some incredible advances.
And human scientists could test
what they've generated to see if it's a valid cure.
Along the way, they'd come up with
more clues in the right direction,
tweaking their algorithm as they go along.
This is an example of the intelligence
augmentation process realized.
AI could also help offer a second diagnosi
for a doctor to help aid in their diagnosis,
giving them yet another perspective to
consider to best help their patient.
The human body is itself
an extremely complicated system,
absolutely rich with data.
AI can help us ask questions
that we never even thought to ask,
and help individual humans by learning
about their specific health needs,
delivering personalized medicine
or treatments when they need it.
The second is software design.
We humans are not the best at writing software.
And when a software project becomes big enough,
like say the Google Chrome browser,
it's hard for a single human, besides Jeff Dean,
to understand the entire code base.
Imagine; a form of programming,
where we give high level input to our machine,
and it decides on the
implementation details by itself.
Take consensus algorithms,
for example; the hype around cryptocurrencies
has been around for almost a decade now,
and we still haven't figured out a wa
to create a scale-able blockchain
consensus algorithm,
that doesn't demand so much electricity to run.
Proof-of-work is a human designed algorithm
and so are the different blockchain
consensus mechanisms.
There's so much theory
that goes into designing these,
from economics to cryptography
to distributed systems,
to sometimes even physics.
It's a hard problem that will require
a radically different way of thinking
to come up with the solution;
perfect for an AI.
Google's AutoML is one example of
AI automated software design.
It learns how to tune hyper-parameters
for specific models,
and companies can use this all-in-one solution
to fit their business needs.
Just give it a data set, and an objective,
and in the ideal scenario,
it learns which model to use,
what its hyper-parameters should be,
and how it should clean and regularize the data.
And this principle of AI assisted design
doesn't just have to apply to software;
it can be any creative endeavor.
Brandmark uses AI to generate a whole host of
potential logos and themes for a new startup.
Just give it some initial parameters
of what you want,
and watch as it gives you many options.
And Google's Magenta project has resulted in
some very cool web demos
that let humans play music alongside AI.
The AI can learn your style of playing,
and adapt, and you can do the same.
In this way, the duet becomes
greater than the sum of its parts.
In fact, for any idea that we have,
we can use AI to visualize it,
assess the different possibilities,
and pick the best one,
be it a scientific or creative endeavor.
And the third is a personal assistant.
The amount of data in the world doubles every two years.
We are constantly getting flooded
with a whole host of options,
of content, of choices, from the Internet,
and different algorithms
across the applications that we use
are constantly manipulating our behavior,
tweaking our opinions and
attention through subtle design tricks,
engineering the reward signals
that are native to human psychology,
to get us to do something;
whether that's clicking on an ad
or buying a specific product,
we have to parse through
all this noise for ourselves,
to see what is the most meaningful to us.
This is a very, very hard task.
A personal AI assistant, stored locally,
trained on our data, with a transparent backend,
could help us navigate the complexity of life
in ways we did not think possible.
It could know us better than any human could,
concatenating data points about us,
from our web browsing history, to our heart rate;
it could tell us how to best achieve our goals,
whether that's in fitness or
in school, in a career or in a relationship.
We can use this feedback
to help guide our own decisions.
Move 37 also catalyzed
the current AI renaissance
that China is currently undergoing.
In the West, Go isn't as common a game,
but in China, it's a highly respected game,
many even believing that it's a sacred game,
connecting humans
to the universe in its complexity.
AlphaGo defeating the world champion at a game
thought to be so sacred in China was huge;
bigger than in the West,
because the general population
is more familiar
with just how complex the game is.
The Chinese government promptly created
an AI development plan
to become the world leader in AI by 2030
and it's definitely executing on it.
Ultimately, automation technology will help
free humans from labor based jobs,
and create new classes of jobs
that we actually enjoy doing.
I hope you liked the video!
Please subscribe for more, and for now,
I've gotta try to play Go... somehow.
So... thanks for watching!