Hi everybody, welcome back
to Arxiv insights.
So, lately, we've seen a lot of
new emerging algorithms
in deep reinforcement learning.
In this episode,
I want to dive into
one specific algorithm
called proximal policy optimization
that was designed at OpenAI
and has proven successful
on a wide variety of tasks
going all the way from robotic control
to Atari and even playing
complicated video games
like Dota 2.
Now, in this episode,
I'm going to dive into some
pretty technical terrain.
So, I think it's good
if you're a little bit prepared.
I've made a few previous videos
with an introduction to
reinforcement learning
and the problem of
the sparse reward setting.
So, I think if you're kind of new
to the field of
reinforcement learning,
I would suggest to watch
those videos first,
and then come back to this video,
as we're going to dive
pretty deep into the rabbit hole,
and being well-prepared
definitely as a must
for this video.
But, if you think you're ready for it,
grab a cup of coffee,
and get ready to dive in deep.
Because, this episode is
on proximal policy optimization.
My name is Xander.
And welcome to our Arxiv Insights.
[Laughter]
[Music]
All right, let's start by
sketching some surroundings first.
If we're doing supervised learning
on a data set like ImageNet,
for example,
then we can have a
static training data set.
We can run a stochastic
gradient descent optimizer
in that data
and we can be pretty sure
that our model will converge
to a pretty decent local optimum.
The road to success
in reinforcement learning, however,
isn't that simple.
One of the problems that
reinforcement learning suffers from
is, that the training data
that is generated,
is itself dependent
on the current policy.
Because, our agent is
generating its own training data
by interacting with the environment,
rather than relying
on a static data set
as is the case in supervised do.
So, this means that
the data distributions
of our observations and rewards
are constantly changing
as our agent learns,
which is a major cause of instability
in the whole training process.
An apart from having this problem
with varying
training data distributions,
reinforcement learning also suffers
from a very high sensitivity
to hyperparameter tuning
and things like initialization,
for example.
In some cases, it's kind of intuitive
to understand why this happens,
because imagine that your
learning rate is too large.
Well, then you could have
a policy update
that pushes your policy network
into a region of the parameter space,
where it's going to collect
the next batch of data
under a very poor policy
causing it to never recover again.
To address many of
these annoying problems
in reinforcement learning,
the team and OpenAI designed a
new reinforcement learning algorithm.
That's called proximal
policy optimization,
or PPO.
The core purpose behind PPO was
to strike a balance
between ease of implementation,
sample efficiency,
and ease of tuning.
Now, the first thing to
realize about PPO
is that it is what we call
a policy gradient method.
This means that unlike
popular key learning approaches,
like DQN, for example,
that can learn from
stored offline data,
proximal policy optimization
learns online.
This means that it doesn't use
a replay buffer to
store past experiences,
but instead it learns directly from
whatever its agent encounters
in the environment.
Once a batch of experience
has been used
to do a gradient update,
the experience is then discarded
and the policy moves on.
This also means that
policy gradient methods
are typically less sample efficient
than queue learning methods, because
they only use
the collected experience once
for doing an update.
A general policy optimization methods
usually start by defining
the policy gradient laws
as the expectation over
the log of the policy actions
times an estimate of
the advantage function.
Okay, so what does that all mean?
Well, the first term pi theta
is our policy.
It's a neural network that
takes the observed states
from the environment as an input
and suggests actions
to take as an output.
The second term is
the advantage function A,
which basically tries to estimate
what the relative value is
of the selected action
in the current state.
Let's take apart what that means.
In order to compute the advantage,
we need two things.
We need a discounted sum of rewards,
and we need a baseline estimate.
So, the first part is
the discounted sum of rewards,
or the return.
This is basically a weighted sum of
all the rewards the agent got
during each time step
in the current episode.
And then, the discount factor gamma,
which is usually somewhere
between 0.9 and 0.99,
accounts for the fact that
your agent cares more about reward,
that is going to get very quickly,
versus the same reward
it would get
a hundred timesteps for now.
This is exactly the same idea
as interest in the financial world.
In the sense that
getting money tomorrow
is usually more valuable
than getting
the same amount of money,
say, a year from now.
So, notice that
the advantage is calculated
after the episode sequence
was collected
from the environment.
In other words,
we know all the rewards.
So, there is no guessing involved
in computing the discount or return,
because we actually
know what happened.
Okay, so that was the first part
of the advantage function
the discounted sum of rewards.
And then, the second part of
the advantage function
is the baseline
or the value function.
Basically, what the
value function tries to do
is give an estimate
of the discounted sum
of rewards from this point onward.
Basically, it's trying to guess
what the final return is
going to be in this episode
starting from the current state.
During training, this neural net
that's representing
the value function
is going to be frequently updated,
using the experience that
our agent collects
in the environment.
Because, this is basically
a supervised learning problem.
You're taking states as an input,
and your neural net is
trying to predict
what the discounted sum of
rewards is going to be
from this state onwards.
So, basic supervised learning.
Notice that because
this value estimate
is the output of a neural net,
this is going to be a noisy estimate.
There's going to be some variance,
because our network is not going to
always predict the exact value
of that states.
So, basically, we're going to
end up with a noisy estimate
of the value function.
Okay, so now we have the
two terms that we need.
We have the discounted sum
of rewards
that we computed from
our episode rollout,
and we have an expectation
an estimate of that value given
the state that we're in.
If we then subtract
the baseline estimate
from the actual return we got,
we get what we call
the advantage estimate.
So, basically, the advantage estimate
is answering the question
"how much better
was the action that I took"
based on the expectation of
what would normally happen
in the state that I was in.
So, basically, was the action
that our agent took
was it better than expected
or was it worse.
So then, by multiplying
the log probabilities
of your policy actions
with this advantage function,
we get the final
optimization objective
that is used in policy grading.
If you think about what
this objective function is doing,
it's intuitively satisfying.
Because, if the advantage
estimate was positive,
meaning that the actions
that the agent took
in the sample trajectory
resulted in better than
average return,
what we'll do is
we'll increase the probability
of selecting them again
in the future
when we encounter
in the same state.
If, on the other hand,
the advantage function
was negative,
then we'll reduce the likelihood
of the selected actions
which makes total sense.
As I've already mentioned,
one of the problems is that
if you simply keep
running gradient descent
on one batch of collected experience,
what will happen is that
you'll update the parameters
in your network
so far outside of the range,
where this data was collected,
that, for example,
the advantage function,
which is, in principle,
a noisy estimate
of the real advantage
is going to be completely wrong.
So, in a sense, you're just
going to destroy your policy,
if you keep running gradient descent
on a single batch of
collected experience.
To solve this issue,
one successful approach
is to make sure that
if you're updating the policy,
you're never going to move too far away
from the old policy.
Now, this idea was widely introduced
in a paper called trust region
policy optimization,
or TRPO, which is actually
the whole basis
on which PPO was built.
Here is the objective function
that was used in TRPO.
If you compare this with
the previous objective function
for vanilla policy gradients,
what you can see is
that the only thing
that changed in this formula
is that the log operator is replaced
with the division by pi theta old.
Now, the slide here shows that
optimizing this TRPO objective
is, in fact, identical to
vanilla policy gradients.
I'm not going to go into
the derivation details here.
But, if you want, you can pause
the video or check out lecture 5
of the deep RL bootcamp
which will take you deep down
the rabbit hole.
Link in the description.
To make sure that the updated policy
doesn't move too far away
from the current policy,
TRPO adds a KL constraint
to the optimization objective.
What this KL constraint
effectively does
is it's just going to make sure
that the new updated policy
doesn't move too far away
from the old policy.
So, in a sense, we just want
to stick close to the region
where we know everything works fine.
The problem is that this KL constraint
adds additional overhead
to our optimization process,
and can sometimes lead to very
undesirable training behavior.
So wouldn't it be nice,
if we can somehow
include this extra constraint directly
into our optimization objective.
Well, as you might have guessed,
that is exactly what PPO does.
OK. So, now that we have
a little bit of surroundings,
let's dive into the crux
of the algorithm.
The central optimization objective
behind PPO.
Hold on to your heads,
it's about to get
a little technical.
The first, let's define
a variable r theta,
which is just a probability ratio,
between the new updated policy outputs
and the outputs of the previous
old version of the policy network.
Given a sequence of
sampled actions and states,
this r theta value
will be larger than 1,
if the action is more likely now
than it was in the
old version of the policy.
It will be somewhere between 0 and 1,
if the action is less likely now
than it was, before
the last gradient step.
If we multiply this ratio r theta
with the advantage function,
we get the normal TRPO objective
in a more readable form.
With this notation,
we can finally write down
the central objective function
that is used in PPO.
Here it is.
Looks surprisingly simple, right?
Well, first of all,
you can see that the objective function
that PPO optimizes is
an expectation operator.
So, this means that
we're going to compute this
over batches of trajectories.
And, this expectation operator is taken
over the minimum of two terms.
The first of these terms is r theta
times the advantage estimate.
This is the default objective
for normal policy gradients
which pushes the policy
towards actions
that yield a high positive advantage
over the baseline.
Now, the second term is very similar
to the first one,
except that it contains
a truncated version
of this r theta ratio
by applying a clipping operation
between 1 minus epsilon
and 1 plus epsilon,
where epsilon is usually
something like 0.2.
Lastly, the min operator
is applied to the two terms
to get the final result.
While this function looks
rather simple at first sight,
fully appreciating all
the subtleties at work here
takes a little bit more effort.
So bear with me here,
I promise we're almost there.
Firstly, it's important to note
that the advantage estimate
can be both positive and negative.
And, this changes the effect
of the main operator.
Here is a plot of
the objective function
for both positive
and negative values
of the advantage estimate.
On the left half of the diagram,
where the advantage function
is positive,
or all the cases
where the selected action
had a better-than-expected effect
on the outcome.
And on the right half of the diagram,
we can find situations
where the action had
an estimated negative effect
on the outcome.
Now, on the left side,
notice how the loss function
flattens out
when r gets too high.
This happens when the action is
a lot more likely under
the current policy,
than it was under the old policy.
In this case we don't want to overdo
the action update too much,
and so the objective function
gets clipped here
to limit the effect
of the gradient update.
Then, on the right side where
the action had
an estimated negative value,
the objective flattens
when R goes near zero.
This corresponds to actions
that are much less likely now
than in the old policy,
and it will have the same effect
of not overdoing
a similar update
which might otherwise reduce
these action probabilities to 0.
Remember, the advantage function
is noisy,
so we don't want to destroy
a policy based on a single estimate.
Finally, what about
the very right hand side?
Well, the objective function
only ends up in this region,
when the last gradient step
made the selected action
a lot more probable,
so r is big,
while also making our policy worse,
since the advantage is negative here.
If that's the case,
then we would really want to
undo the last gradient step.
It just so happens that
the objective function
in PPO allows us to do this.
The function is negative here,
so the gradient will tell us
to walk the other direction
and make the action less probable
by an amount proportional to
how much we screwed it up
in the first place.
And also, know this
that this is the only region where
the unclipped part of
the objective function
has a lower value
than the clipped version,
and those gets returned
by the minimization operator.
Pretty clever, right?
If you're wondering how on earth
the authors from
the PPO paper managed to
design this specific reward function,
well, it's quite likely
that they had an intuitive idea
of what they wanted
the objective function to do.
So, they probably sketched
a bunch of diagrams
that satisfied the behavior
that we just discussed,
and then came up with
the exact objective function
to make it all work out.
Don't worry if you didn't fully get
all the little details involved.
Basically, the PPO objectives
does the same as a TRP all objective,
and that it forces the policy updates
to be conservative,
if they move very far away
from the current policy.
The only difference is
that PPO does this
with a very simple objective function
that doesn't require to calculate
all these additional constraints
or KL divergences.
In fact, it turns out that
the simple PPO objective function
often outperforms
the more complicated variant
that we have in TRPO.
Simplicity often wins.
All right, nice.
Now, that we've seen
the central objective function
behind PPO.
Let's take a look at
the entire algorithm end to end.
As mentioned before,
there are two alternating
threads in PPO.
In the first one,
the current policy is
interacting with the environment,
generating episode sequences,
for which we immediately calculate
the advantage function
using our fitted baseline estimate
for the state values.
And then every so many episodes,
a second thread
is going to collect all that experience
and run gradient descent
on the policy network
using the clips PPO objective.
As was done in training
the opening i5 system,
these two threats can actually
be decoupled from each other
by using thousands of remote workers
that interact with the environment
using a recent copy
of the policy network
and a GPU cluster
that runs gradient descent
on the network weights
using the collected experience
from those workers.
Note that, in this case,
each worker has to
refresh its local copy of
the policy network pretty often
to make sure that
it's always running with
the latest version
of the policy network
to keep everything nicely balanced.
Now, importantly,
the final loss function
that is used to train an agent
is the sum of
this clips PPO objective,
that we just saw,
plus two additional terms
The first additional term
of the loss function
is basically in charge of
updating the baseline network.
This is the part of
the network graph,
that is in charge of estimating
how good it is to be in this state.
Or more specifically,
what is the average amount of
this counted reward
that I expect to get
from this point onwards.
Even though the value
and policy outputs
form two separate heads
of the same network,
because they are part of
the same computation graph,
you can actually combine everything
in a single loss function
and the auto differentiation library
will just figure out where
to send all the gradients.
The reason that
these two lost terms are
actually part of
the same objective function
is that the value estimation
network shares
a large portion of its parameter space
with the policy network.
The intuition is that
whether you're trying to estimate
the value of the current state,
or you simply want to take
the best current action,
you're likely going to need
very similar feature
extraction pipelines
from the current state observation.
So these parts of the network
are simply shared.
Then, finally, the last term
in the objective function is called
the entropy term.
This term is in charge of
making sure that our agent
does enough exploration
during training.
In contrast to discrete
action policies
that output the action
choice probabilities,
the PPO policy head
outputs the parameters
of a Gaussian distribution
for each available action type.
When running the agent
and training mode,
the policy will then sample
from these distributions
to get a continuous output value
for each action head.
Now, if you want to fully understand
why the entropy term
encourages exploration,
I really recommend
to check out Aurelien Gero's video
on the ideas behind entropy
and KL divergence in machine learning.
The link is in the description.
Basically, the entropy
of a stochastic variable,
which is driven by
an underlying probability distribution,
is the average amount of bits
that is needed to
represent its outcome.
It is a measure of how unpredictable
an outcome of this variable really is.
So, maximizing its entropy
will force it to have a wide spread
over all the possible options,
resulting in the most
unpredictable outcome.
So this gives some intuition,
as to why adding an entropy term,
will push the policy
to behave a little bit more randomly
until the other parts of the objective
start dominating.
As always we have a couple of
hyperparameters
c1 and c2
that weights the contributions
of these different parts
in the loss function.
For people that want to
take a deeper look
at PPO in terms of Python code,
I really recommend to check out
this implementation
in PyTorch from RL-Adventure.
Trust me. Even though you've
never worked with PyTorch,
this implementation is
as clean as it gets.
If you're looking for
a more production proof implementation,
I would recommend to check out
OpenAI baselines,
which has a full implemented
tensorflow version
that runs on different environments
like Atari MuJoCo and others.
Both links are in the description.
All right, so that's it.
Congratulations,
if you've made it this far,
we've covered all you need to know
about proximal policy optimization.
In the paper, you can find
a bunch of graphs
that compare PPO to
other benchmarks in deep RL.
Don't hesitate to have a look.
The link is in the description.
The important thing
to remember though
is that PPO wasn't
specifically designed
for sample efficiency,
but rather to address
the really complicated code
that was needed for
a lot of other algorithms.
And, also, you know making it
relatively easy to tune
in terms of hyperparameters.
And, because PPO achieves
both of those objectives
while also yielding close to
or above state-of-the-art performance
on a wide range of tasks,
it has become one of the benchmarks
in deep reinforcement learning.
In summary,
PPO is a state of the art policy
gradient method
the algorithm has the stability
and reliability of TRPO
while much simpler to implement
requiring only a few tweaks
to vanilla policy gradient methods,
and it can be used for a wide range
of reinforcement learning tasks.
Great.
Before I end this video,
I would really like to thank
all the people that support
this channel on patreon.
Even if it's only $1 a month,
those contributions really mean
a lot to me.
They are a big motivation,
because they show that
the people out there
really care for the content
that I'm making
and it's a really good motivation
to keep going.
So, thanks a lot, all my great
amazing patreon supporters.
That was it for this episode.
Thank you very much for watching.
I hope you learned something about
proximal policy optimization.
Don't forget to like,
subscribe, and share,
and I'd love to see you again
in the next episode
of Arxiv Insights.
[Music]