Hello, and welcome back to
another reinforcement learning
coding tutorial.
We've come a long way since the beginning.
For about half this series,
you struggled through a boring
grid world environments
as you learn the basics
of the Bellman equation,
dynamic programming, and Q learning.
Now, we're finally at the point
where it's time to reveal the
absolute cutting edge
industry standard algorithm
which produces stellar results
on a variety of
reinforcement learning tasks
in both continuous, and
discrete action spaces.
The good news is that
it's already built on top of
the actor critic architecture
we learned.
So, all we need to implement it
are a few tweaks and improvements
to everything we've learned
over the last few tutorials.
If you're not an ethical person,
please turn off this tutorial now
because we don't want you
building robots to destroy humans.
Do you want to destroy humans?
Please, say no.
Ok. I will destroy humans.
If your ethical,
there are so many ways
we can use this technology
to benefit and uplift humanity.
There are a couple main problems
with the standard actor critic methods
which were inhibiting results.
First, training was extremely sensitive
to hyperparameter tuning.
It took a lot of experimentation
to make things work.
Second, outlier data resulting in
extreme policy updates
could throw the entire
training process out of whack
where bad actions lead to
inaccurate values
and the downward spiral
becomes unrecoverable.
You can see this
on the tensor board graph,
if the reward just tanks.
I ran into this myself playing
with the actor critic.
The folks at OpenAI designed
proximal policy optimization
with three main goals in mind.
One, keeping the code simple
and easy to implement.
Number two, sample efficiency.
Policy gradients are online methods
which means we can only train on data
obtained from the latest policy.
This means we have to play
a lot of episodes.
PPO is designed to obtain
maximum efficiency
from the training data we capture.
Third, minimal hyper parameter tuning.
Sane defaults just work.
PPO includes several upgrades
built on top of the
actor critic algorithm.
What do they all have in common?
They seek to maintain smooth
gradual gradient updates,
so we get continuous improvement
and avoid unrecoverable crashes.
The first major upgrade is called
generalized advantage estimation,
or GAE.
This helps smooth the discounter
rewards and reduce variance
to make training smoother
and more stable.
Next is using a surrogate
policy loss function.
The policy loss function
in PPO is a ratio
between the new probabilities
and the old probabilities
times the advantage.
And, we take the minimum between
this surrogate function
and a clip version.
This ensures a very gradual
policy update.
The third innovation are
mini-batch updates.
A long series of experiences sampled
and these trajectories are
broken into random mini batches.
And, the network is gradually updated
over a fixed number of epochs.
Let's look at
each one of these in detail.
Generalize advantage estimation
is a way of calculating returns
and advantages which reduces variance
to give us smoother network updates.
The smoothing is governed by
a hyperparameter
called lambda between 0 and 1.
A lambda of 1 gives
the highest accuracy.
Lower values have greater smoothing,
but higher bias.
Bias being the deviance
from the correct value.
But, less variance then
the smoother training.
The PPO paper suggests
using a lambda of 0.95.
Let's look at the
complete GAE algorithm.
One, mask is 0 if the state
is terminal episode,
or otherwise one.
We init the GAE variable to 0,
and loop backwards from
the last step in our data.
We set delta to the reward plus gamma
times the value of state prime
times the mask.
So, if the mask is 0,
it totally counts
without the value of state prime
since the episode is done.
Minus the value of
the original state.
Four, we update GAE as
delta plus gamma
times lambda times a mask
times the previous value of GAE.
Five, the return for the state
and action is
GAE plus the value of the state.
So earlier, we subtracted
the value of the state
to get the advantage.
Now, to get the full return,
we're adding it back
into the GAE we calculated.
Number 6, we reverse
the list of returns
back into the correct order,
since we are looping backward
to start with.
Now let's move on to
the surrogate policy loss function.
The major difference in PPO is
how the actor loss is calculated.
Let's take a look.
As stated before,
the biggest problem with
policy gradient methods is
ensuring gentle updates.
The PPO loss function is based on
the ratio of new probabilities
to old probabilities.
Logarithmic spaces is calculated with
new log problems minus old log probs
and then exponentiated.
A long trajectory of experience
is collected
prior to each update cycle.
The old log probabilities are
saved with each action.
With each successive update,
we calculate the new log probability
to plug into the ratio.
The policy actor loss in PPO is
a minimum of two surrogate functions.
Surrogate 1 is the ratio we calculated
times the advantage.
Surrogate 2 is the ratio clip
between 1 minus epsilon and
1 plus epsilon times the advantage.
The PPO paper suggests using
an epsilon of 0.2,
which clips the ratio
between 0.8 and 1.2.
Value loss stays the same as
an actor critic
the mean squared error
between the actual calculated returns,
and the value returned by the network.
If you want to dive into
some technical details about
how this works and why it works,
as a great 20-minute video
by Arxiv Insights,
which I will link in the description.
Just beware the octopus slap,
and also,
when you go to the beach,
watch out for monkeys.
Finally, let's have a look at
the PPO update algorithm.
Step 1, collect a batch of
n transitions,
numbering in the thousands,
and it should be a multiple of
the mini batch size
from parallel environments.
Specifically, we're going to
save the state, action,
log probabilities of the action,
the reward obtained,
the done mask, and the value of
the state for each step.
Step 2, calculate the returns
for the save transitions
using the GAE algorithm.
Step 3, calculate the advantage,
which is the returns
we just calculated
minus the values of the states.
Four, we're going to loop for e epochs.
One, sample enough random mini batches
from stored transitions to
cover the entire batch.
Two, pass the state
into the network
to get the action,
value of state prime,
entropy, and new log probabilities
of the action.
Three, calculate the surrogate
policy loss, and mean squared error loss.
Four, back propagate the total loss
through the network.
Finally, we repeat all of the above,
until our training converges
and we're happy with
the rewards were getting.
All right, let's have a look
at the code.
First, let's look at
the neural network.
This is the exact same model we use
with our actor critic.
It's designed for
continuous action tasks.
The only difference is that
we're using the normal distribution
to help her from PyTorch
to sample actions from
the Gaussian distribution,
calculate the log probabilities, etc.
rather than doing it manually.
The other slight difference is that
we're using the standard deviation
as a separate parameter,
not connected to any other layers
in the network.
This works just as well,
but is more efficient.
Note that, this network architecture
could easily be adopted
to work with a discrete action space
by removing the
standard deviation parameter,
and changing the
normal distribution class
to a discrete distribution.
All right.
Now, let's look at the hyper parameter
as we use in training.
First up, NUM_ENVS.
That's the number of environments
will run in parallel
to generate the training data.
HIDDEN_SIZE.
The number of neurons in
the hidden layer of our neural network.
LEARNING_RATE.
This is what we passed
the atom optimizer.
GAMMA.
The discount factor used
to calculate returns.
GAE_LAMBDA.
This is the smoothing factor used
in the GAE algorithm
which we previously discussed.
PPO_EPSILON.
This is used to clip the ratio
between the new policy
and the old policy.
A value of 0.2 will clip the ratio
between 0.8 and 1.2.
CRITIC_DISCOUNT.
The critic loss tends to be
quite a bit bigger
than the actor loss,
so we can scale it down
using this value.
0.5 seems to work very well
and improve training.
ENTROPY_BETA.
The amount of importance we give
to the entropy bonus
which improves exploration and
was discussed in previous tutorials.
PPO_STEPS.
The number of transitions we sample
for each training iteration.
Keep in mind each step
collects a transition
from each parallel environment.
The total amount of data collected
will be multiplied
by NUM_ENVS from above.
256 steps times 8 environments
gives us a buffer of
2048 data samples to train on.
MINI_BATCH_SIZE.
The number of samples
that are randomly selected
from the total amount of stored data.
PPO_EPOCHS.
One epoch means one pass over
the entire buffer of training data,
so if the training buffer
has 2048 transitions
and then mini batch sizes 64,
one epoch would be
32 randomly selected mini batches.
If PPO_EPOCHS is set to 10,
will propagate the network
over the entire buffer of
training data
ten times.
This will make more sense
when we get into the code below.
TEST_EPOCHS.
This is a count of
how often we'll run tests
to evaluate the performance
of our network.
Here one epoch is an entire
PPO update cycle.
Again, this will make sense
when you see the code.
NUM_TESTS.
This is the number of tests we run
to average the total rewards
each time we want to evaluate
the performance of the network.
And finally, TARGET_REWARD.
When we reach this reward
our evaluation will stop training.
Now, let's jump to the main loop,
and I'll explain other stuff
as we get to it.
The first interesting thing is
how we're handling
parallel environments.
When we call envs.reset,
it returns a list of 8 states.
One for each parallel environment
that we created.
When we step we pass
a list of eight actions
and it gives us back 8 rewards,
8 next states, and 8 dones.
Moving down, we initialize
the network,
the optimizer, and track
the training step.
Train epoch which refers
to one complete update cycle
and best reward.
We enter the main loop
and create empty lists
to store training data.
Now, we loop through
the number of PPO steps.
Keep in mind that
each PPO step generates
a state action reward,
next state transition from each environment.
We pass a current state
through the network
to get the probability distribution
and estimated value of the state.
Also, remember that each state is
really a list of states
one for each environment.
Reward, done,
the distribution, and value
all contain a batch of information
from each environment.
We sample an action.
Before we calculated
the log probabilities manually,
now, we're using a helper function
from the normal distribution class.
We store the log probabilities,
values, rewards, done masks,
states, and actions in a list.
Each list will be PPO steps long,
and each step contains
a list NUM_ENVS wide.
In order to calculate
the returns correctly,
we run the final next state
through the network to get its value.
In order to calculate
the returns correctly,
we run the final next state
through the network to get its value.
Now, let's take a look at
the generalized advantage
estimation function.
Input is the next value,
the list of rewards,
a list of done masks,
and the list of values.
Keep in mind that
each step of the inputs
contains data across
each parallel environment.
We look backward from
the most recent experience to earlier.
Delta is just the Bellman equation
minus the value of the state.
It is essentially
the same as the advantage.
I recall from the Bellman equation
that if the episode is over
we use just a reward
as a terminal state
has no next state.
So, if an episode is done,
multiplying by a mask of zero
will zero out state prime.
You can see GAE is essentially
a moving average
of advantages discounted by
gamma times a GAE lambda
0.99 times 0.95
comes out to about 0.94.
To calculate the return,
we add the value of the state
we previously subtracted back in.
The return is prepend into the list
in order to get
the correct order back,
since we're looping in reverse.
Again, returns is
a list PPO steps long and
the number of environments
we're using wide.
Jumping back down into
the main loop,
we concatenate each list
inside a torch tensor.
So, a list that was 256 steps long
and eight environments wide,
simply becomes 2048 steps along.
In the PPO paper, each step of
this process training data
containing states, actions,
log_probs, returns, and advantages
is referred to as a trajectory.
Just as a side note,
I found the number one place
I get confused,
when I'm looking at
machine learning code is
with tensor sizes.
Dimensions can be confusing,
and if they don't match
the code won't run.
If you ever get stuck
or don't understand something,
try printing out the tensor shapes
before and after an operation
to get a feel for it.
We calculate the advantages
by subtracting the calculator
returns from
the network estimated values
of each state.
We then normalize them by
subtracting the mean of the list
and dividing by
the standard deviation.
This helps make training
go even smoother.
Now, the trajectories get passed
in the PPO update function.
Let's take a look.
First, some initialization code
to track statistics.
Now, we loop over
the chosen number of PPO epochs.
The PPO iterator function
generates random mini-batches
covering the our update batch.
So if the update batch
contains 2048 trajectories
and the mini batch size is 64,
it will generate
32 mini batches per epoch.
We pass a state into the network
to get the latest
probability distribution
and value of the state.
From this, we calculate the entropy,
and the new log probabilities
of the originally selected actions.
Now, we calculate the ratio of
the new probability divided
by the old probability.
But since we're dealing in
a logarithmic space,
you subtract and then exponentiate.
Surrogate 1 is the ratio
times the advantage.
Surrogate 2 is a clipped ratio
The actor loss is the negative of
the minimum of those two surrogates.
The critic loss is
the mean squared error
between the actual GAE returns
and the network estimated
value of the state.
The final loss is the discounted
critic loss cut in half
plus the actor loss
minus the entropy bonus
scaled by beta.
We run back propagation as usual.
We track statistics and write them
to tensor board to visualize.
Now, back to the main code.
One test epoch is
one entire update operation
like you just saw.
Every few epochs, we run
a series of tests
and average the total rewards
to see if our agents performance
is improving or worsening.
The more tests you run,
the more accurate
the statistics will be,
but the longer it will take.
Every time we achieve
a new best-ever reward,
we save a check point.
If the test reward has
exceeded our target,
then we stop training.
Let's take a quick look at
the test code.
When we are training,
we want a sample action semi-randomly
from the probability distribution
output by the network.
This is so we get exploration.
But, when we were testing
the performance of our code
most the time we want the results
to be deterministic
and not random.
But, when we were testing
the performance of our code,
most of the time,
we want the results
to be deterministic
rather than random.
A continuous action space
instead of
sampling based on the mean
and standard deviation.
We simply use the mean.
A discrete action space,
we would take the argmax
or the action with
the highest probability.
This function simply runs
through one episode,
and returns a total reward.
That's all the code.
To run it, you'll need to
install Roboschool.
Unlike MuJoCo which is commercial,
Roboschool is completely free.
But, it requires Mac or Linux.
The installation process is
a bit of a pain,
but it should work if you follow
the exact instructions
in their Github repo.
There's a link at the top of the code.
Let's take a look at the results.
I was able to get very stellar results
on Roboschool Half Cheetah,
and only about 40 minutes with my GPU.
Now, it's time for some homework.
First, I want you to play around with
other continuous environments
either from Roboschool
or from OpenAI Gym.
Second, try modifying this PPO code
to play Atari games
with a discrete action space.
It's not too complicated.
First, you have to remove
the standard deviation parameter
from the network.
Second, you've got to change
the normal distribution class
we're using
to torch's categorical
distribution class.
Third, in the test_env function,
sample the argmax of probabilities
instead of the mean.
Fourth, add the Atari rapper's
from the other tutorials back
into them make_env function.
Alright, post your results
in the comments or
in our Slack channel.
I look forward to seeing
what you can achieve with this code.
Congratulations, you've come
a long long way
on your reinforcement learning journey.
You grew from basic
Bellman equation calculations,
and grid world kindergarten
to the most advanced RL algorithm
and production use today.
If you've learned absolutely
nothing else from this tutorial,
you should know one thing.
Next time, Naughty by Nature asks you
"If you're down with OPP?".
You should respond,
"No bro, I PPO".
All right, I'm Colin Skow.
I still have one more ace up my sleeve
to help turn cutting edge AI research
into code you can understand.
I'll see you very soon
in the next tutorial.
Meanwhile, happy coding.