Hello, world! It's Siraj.
What's the most efficient way
to interact with the database?
Anytime we want to create, read,
update, or delete data
in a database.
We'll usually do so
in the form of SQL queries.
SQL stands for structured query language.
It's the standard language used
to communicate with relational databases.
What about Haskell DB?
Each query takes a certain amount of
time to compute.
Ideally, we can order our queries
in the most computationally
efficient way.
There are several techniques
to do this.
And, usually, reinforcement learning
isn't considered one of them.
But, a recent paper showed
that using a deep Q network,
researchers were able to
perform queries
twice as fast as using
standard techniques.
We'll learn how they did it
in this video.
But first, we'll need to
understand why
they used reinforcement learning
as opposed to other more
common techniques.
We know that reinforcement learning
works great for video games.
Games are the perfect testbed
for implementing RL algorithms,
since they're constrained environments
where time is an element
that allows for rapid experimentation.
The Markov decision process
is the mathematical framework of choice
for framing this decision problem
that our AI or agent is facing.
It consists of a few variables
that define our environment,
our agent,
and how our agent interacts
with this environment.
In reinforcement learning,
an agent tries to come up with
the best action to take
given a state.
In the video game Pac-Man,
the state would be
the 2d game world were in,
that includes the surrounding items
like enemies walls and packed dots.
The action would be
moving through this 2d space,
which would be going either
up, down, left, or right.
So, given the state of our game world,
our agent will need to pick
the best action to take
in order to maximize rewards.
We know that eating packed dots
gives us positive rewards,
and getting eaten by a ghost
gives us a negative reward,
and a possible temper tantrum
which we want to avoid.
Through trial and error,
our agent will accumulate knowledge
of the environment
through state action pairs.
Meaning it can tell if there would be
a positive or negative reward
given a state action pair.
We can represent this using
the Q function,
where Q stands for quality,
as in it assesses the quality of
a given state action pair.
We can actually learn what
the optimal Q value
will be at any given point.
This is called Q learning.
By using what's called the Bellman equation,
we can write out an equation
that relates the value of one state
to the value of another state
in our environment.
Because we are able to relate states
across time to each other
mathematically
using the bellman equation.
We can use any number of methods
to iteratively approximate
our Q function.
But, in the case of
our Pac-Man environment
the state action space
can get really big.
In fact, at some point,
it will no longer be feasible
to store all the state action pairs.
Of course we could
still perform Q learning,
but it'll get harder to approximate
the Q function over time.
Luckily for us, there exists
a universal function approximator
called a neural network.
If we give it enough input data,
it can learn any function.
If we use a neural network as an agent
that predicts the Q value based on
the input state action pair,
then we have a much more
tractable solution
than storing every possible value
like we did previously.
To capture all the intricate details
of this knowledge present
in our Q table,
we'll likely need to add
a few hidden layers to our network.
Making it a deep neural network.
The extra hidden layers allow
the network to internally
come up with features
that can help it learn complex functions
that would have been impossible
using a more shallow network.
We can call this whole process
deep reinforcement learning,
and more specifically deep Q learning.
Now, let's bring this theory
back to reality.
You and I have neural networks
in our head.
Networks of neurons are firing
in endlessly different combinations
to approximate functions that help us
perform a wide variety of tasks
as we go about our lives.
We can consider our reality
a Markov decision process.
As neural network agents given a state,
we take actions to maximize reward
for whatever task we are achieving
using our function approximation
capabilities to make predictions.
In that way, we can consider
our reality
deep reinforcement learning.
Anytime we use a neural network to
approximate some
reinforcement learning function
(?) a value function, a policy,
even the model itself.
We can call that
deep reinforcement learning.
So, how does this apply to
the problem of query optimization?
Well, we know that SQL statements
are used to perform
a wide variety of tasks
related to the database.
They can update data, retrieve data,
merge data, delete data.
Each SQL query has its own function.
Assume we have a database
consisting of three tables:
employees, salaries, and taxes.
Let's say we want to
calculate the total tax
owed by all employees
under manager one.
We can write out a SQL query
that does that.
We'll compute the tax owed
by each employee
by selecting their specific attributes,
and summing them all up.
This query is going to perform
a three relation join.
We can use J to help denote
the cost of accessing a base relation.
The cost of each query is
the percentage of the total batch cost.
It's the time needed to execute a query.
It's computed different ways,
but almost always takes into account
several computation factors,
such as input, output, CPU,
and communication.
We want to minimize this cost,
so that we perform our queries
as fast as possible.
Using dynamic programming,
we can iteratively calculate the cost
of optimally accessing
the three-base relations.
After the first iteration,
we can build off of this information
that we previously computed and
enumerate all two relations.
When we compute the best cost to
join two relations,
we'll look up the relevant
previously computed results.
In the third iteration,
we'll proceed through
the other two relation sets.
Eventually, finding the final
best costs for
joining all three tables.
Once complete, we'll see that
this algorithm has a
space and time complexity
exponential in the number of relations.
Which is why it's usually only used for
queries between 10 and 20 relations.
When we have more relations than that,
we'll need to use a different
query optimization technique.
Instead of solving this
join ordering problem
using dynamic programming,
what if we formulated this problem
as a Markov decision process,
and solved it using
reinforcement learning.
If we do that, the states can be
considered the remaining relations
to be joined.
The actions would be the valid joins
out of the remaining relations.
The next states would be
the old remaining relations
set with two relations removed,
and the resultant join added.
Lastly, the reward would be
the estimated cost of the new join.
Because, we defined these
Markovian variables,
we can define a Q function
using the bellman equation
to describe the long-term cost of
each join.
Since we've defined a Q function,
we can order joins in a greedy way.
We start with the initial query graph,
find the join with the lowest Q value,
then update the query graph and
repeat the process.
This Q learning algorithm has
a computational complexity of n cubed.
Although that's high,
that's still much lower than
the exponential run time complexity
of dynamic programming.
In reality, though, we don't have
access to the optimal Q function.
So, we need to approximate it.
To do that, we can use
a neural network,
which would make this deep Q learning.
To learn the Q function, we need to
observe past execution data.
We can use it as training data
for our neural network.
Since we're using a neural network
to represent our Q function,
we need to feed the state and
actions into the network
as fixed-length feature vectors.
This helps our network perform
matrix multiplications gracefully,
as it accepts this kind of format.
We'll use one hot vectors
to encode the set of all attributes
present in the query graph,
and the participating attributes
from both the left and right side
of the join.
We'll use a simple two layer
fully connected network as our agent,
and train it using the standard
gradient descent optimization algorithm.
Once trained, it will accept
a SQL query in plaintext,
parse it into
an abstract syntax tree form,
feature the tree,
and use a neural network whenever
a candidate join is scored.
And because, databases are real-time
used in production environments
constantly being updated and changed,
we can periodically retune our network
using the feedback from live execution.
Across all cost models,
deep Q is competitive
with the optimal solution
without a priori knowledge
of the index structure.
We can safely say
that learning-based optimizers
are more robust than
hand designed algorithms.
Because, they can adapt to changes
in data, workload, or cost models.
For the largest joins, deep Q
wins by up to 10,000x
compared to exhaustive enumeration.
Three points to remember
from this video.
Deep reinforcement learning involves
using a neural network
to approximate
reinforcement learning functions
like the Q function.
We can assess the quality or
Q of state action pairs
by computing a Q table.
Q learning involves approximating
the relationship
between state action pairs and Q values
in this table using neural networks.
Please subscribe
for more programming videos.
For now, I've got to take a meeting.
Thanks for watching.